Tissue Culture Association records
Tissue Culture Association records
1940-1997
bulk 1946-1986
1940 1997
Coll016
Tissue Culture Association
108 boxes (100 linear feet)
108 boxes
100 linear feet
Files represent the President, Executive Council, Secretary, Treasurer, Business Office, Committees, Branches, Divisions, conferences, and publications of the Tissue Culture Association. Includes constitutions and bylaws, reports, questionnaires, correspondence, publications (such as the Index of Tissue Culture and the TCA Newsletter), membership information, budgets, and meeting minutes and other conference materials. Additional materials on the W. Alton Jones Cell Science Center and audio, print and ephemeral materials have not been processed and are not included in the collection's finding aid; please contact Special Collections for further information.
University of Maryland, Baltimore County Albin O. Kuhn Library and Gallery UMBC 1000 Hilltop Circle Baltimore, MD 21250 410-455-2353 speccoll@umbc.edu
Series I contains the files of the Tissue Culture Association’s (TCA) presidents. Included are correspondence, constitutions and by-laws, reports and a variety of administrative files including administrative calendars, handbooks, and rosters of officers and committee members. Correspondence dates from the early years, beginning in 1940 when TCA was the Tissue Culture Commission and continues until 1985. Correspondence covers a wide range of topics illustrating the breadth of interests and activities of the Association including the education program, publications, committees, such as public affairs, terminology, placement and nomenclature and the special committee on litigation. Of interest is the series of correspondence concerning the proposed reorganization of the Association that never in fact materialized but resulted in the creation of the American Society for Cell Biology. Copies of the constitutions and by-laws and their revisions begin with the 1949 constitution and are extant through 1984. In addition there are copies of the documents of incorporation and the president’s annual reports for the years 1969 to 1977.
The second series comprises the records of the secretary of the society and are divided into two sub-series: correspondence and membership. There is a significant amount of correspondence, beginning in 1946 with that of the first secretary, Margaret Murray and continuing through the late 1970s. Membership files include a substantial number of membership application files dating from the early 1960s to the mid 1970s as well as member files which include correspondence, invoices and memos, and member rosters beginning in 1947 and continuing until 1982.
Treasurer’s records make up the third series and include correspondence, the annual reports of the Secretary-Treasurer, audits, budgets, expense reports, financial statements, and tax forms. Series IV contains records of the business office. Records date from 1978–1984 and primarily consist of the correspondence of the Executive Director, William Momberger. Also included are disbursement and receipt records for 1982–1984, and miscellaneous files on taxes, unemployment insurance and a surety bond.
Series V, Committees, is comprised of files from a variety of TCA committees. Files for both standing committees and ad hoc committees provide a view of the varied interests and activities of the organization. Files span the years 1951–1985 and include correspondence, reports, memos, and minutes and rosters.
Series VI is made up of files pertaining to the societies Branches and Divisions for the years 1963-1997. Those Branches and Divisions for which documents are extant are: California, Central States, Michigan, Midwestern, Montreal, National Capitol Area, New York, Northeast, Rocky Mountain, Texas, Honor Fell Division, Invertebrate Division, Organic Culture Division, Plant Division. These contain constitutions and by-laws, reports, and correspondence. Also included in this series are files on proposed clubs and sets of rosters.
The seventh series, Meetings, is divided into four sub-series: Executive Council, Annual Meetings, Decennial Review Conference, and Miscellaneous Conferences and Audio Tapes. Files for the first sub-series, Executive Council, contains agendas, minutes and supporting documents for the meetings of the Executive Council for the years 1947–1985. The next sub-series, Annual Meetings, is comprised of files for the annual meetings from 1946–1986. Included are organizational materials including files of the program committees, local committees and exhibits committees along with printed programs, abstracts, reports, minutes, correspondence, and catalogues. The third sub-series, Decennial Review Conference contains the planning documents for three conferences, 1956, 1966, and 1976, along with the minutes, reports, budgets, correspondence, abstracts, directories, and session papers of the actual events. The final sub-series contains files of individual conferences and meetings. Included are document files and audiotapes.
The eighth series, Publications, is made up of three sub-series: Bibliography & Index, Bulletins, Manual, Newsletter, and Miscellaneous Publications, and In Vitro. The first sub-series contains correspondence files with October House, the publisher, as well as general correspondence and printed bibliographies. Included is the first bibliography published in 1953 and continuing until 1966. Also included are correspondence files for the Index of Tissue Culture for the years 1965–1977. The second sub-series contains published copies of the bulletin dating from 1947–1967, correspondence, minutes, manuscripts, and questionnaires pertaining to the TCA Manual, and miscellaneous publications. Also included are copies of the TCA Newsletter beginning in 1968 along with correspondence, memos, and reports connected with that publication. The third sub-series, In Vitro, contains documents relating to the TCA journal, In Vitro. Along with copies of the publication are copies of individual articles, correspondence, subscription ledgers, budgets, page proofs, and sales figures.
On November 10-13, 1946, a conference on tissue culture was held in Hershey, Pennsylvania and sponsored jointly by the panels on cellular physiology, cytochemistry, and nutrition of the Committee on Growth and was paid for by the American Cancer Society. After the final session of the conference a group of sixteen interested persons met to establish an informal organization of investigators who use tissue culture techniques. Primary objectives were discussed and a slate of temporary officers were elected. Keith Porter was elected Chairman, Margaret Murray, secretary, George O. Gey, Duncan Heatherington and C.M. Pomerat, Executives and Honor Fell, European Member at Large.
It was decided that the initial aims of the new Tissue Culture Commission (TCC) would be twofold. The first was to look at kinds of media needed by workers in the field and to examine the possibility of preparing these ingredients at a central lab for distribution at a moderate cost. The second aim was to prepare a bibliography of published research in tissue culture since its inception and cross-index it for publication. In addition it was decided that membership would be open to any investigator using tissue culture methods in research.
The first meeting of the Executive Committee was held in March 1, 1947 at the Rockefeller Institute. At that time, much of the discussion was centered around the subject of media production. It was determined that the TCC should certify the products it offered. In addition, methods for developing the proposed publication of a Bibliography were considered.
In October of 1948, a testing laboratory, where media could be certified for distribution, was set up by Keith Porter at the Sloane-Kettering Institute and was supervised by the Executive Committee. In addition, 1948 saw the first in a series of annual tissue culture courses taught. This first course was held at the University of Toronto, and thereafter at different institutions around the country.
In 1948 and 1949, meetings were held in conjunction with those of the American Association of Anatomists. At the 1949 meeting the first slate of officers was elected with George Gey becoming the first president. At that time the commission adopted a constitution and officially became the Tissue Culture Association (TCA). By this time Dr. Margaret Murray had begun the process of directing the work on the Tissue Culture Bibliography and the initial results of that effort were published in 1952.
By 1958, due to changing conditions, some within the Executive Committee began to feel that it was time to move away from a methods based society and evolve into a new form. To this end a committee was formed to look into the possibility of reorganizing TCA. Discussions centered around the notion that the reorganization would bring into being essentially a new society with a new name but have a continuity of officers and TCA activities. The focus of this new society would be cell biology or cytology. It was determined that a referendum of the membership should be held to determine their views. The results of the letter sent to the entire membership showed that they were generally favorable toward the idea of reorganization. It was decided that one of the first steps should be a change to the TCA constitution and possible names for the newly reorganized society were proposed.
By April 1959 discussions and planning had progressed to the point where an organizing committee was formed, with Keith Porter as chair, to begin the process. On January 9, 1960 this committee met in New York and essentially drew up the blueprint for what would become the American Society for Cell Biology (ASCB). There were some among the membership however, including former officers, who felt that TCA was being railroaded out of existence and that the proposed new society would not adequately represent the interests of all current members. Further, there had been no vote to authorize changes to the TCA constitution and no vote of the membership had been taken. As a result, by the time that the organizing group again met in May of 1960, it had been decided that the two ‘entities’ would run concurrently for a period and they would let nature take its course. Ultimately both TCA and ASCB continued independently and the reorganization of TCA never materialized and in 1964 TCA was incorporated as a non-profit organization in the District of Columbia.
That same year TCA began looking for a more permanent place for their education programs. To this end Dr. Gey met with Mrs. W. Alton Jones, mother of Patricia Edgerton, a scientist at Johns Hopkins Lab. She donated land in Lake Placid, N. Y. as a permanent home for the Society’s education programs. In 1969, a board was formed to manage the new science center with Donald Merchant as Director. In June 1971 the new W. Alton Jones Cell Science Center (WAJCSC) was dedicated.
For some years thereafter the Society was effectively managed out of offices at the WAJCSC though it had no official office on site. Then in 1978 the first Executive Director William Momberger was hired and subsequently the first Executive Office was opened in Gaithersburg, Maryland.
Under the auspices of the national organization, many individual branches were created to meet the needs of specific geographical areas. They were: California, Central States, Michigan, Midwestern, Montreal, National Capitol Area, New York, Northeast, Rocky Mountain, Texas. In addition, there were specific divisions within the organization such as the Honor Fell Division, the Invertebrate Division, the Organic Culture Division, and the Plant Division.
Over the years, TCA has put out a number of publications the first of which was the bibliography titled Index of Tissue Culture, initially published in 1952. Other publications followed such as the official TCA journal In Vitro, the Bulletin, and the TCA Newsletter along with many ‘special’ publications.
At the Annual Meeting in June of 1994 the Society voted to change the name to the Society for In Vitro Biology (SIVB). The SIVB offices are currently in Largo, Maryland.
Organized into nine series:
Series I. President
Correspondence
Administrative Files
Series II. Secretary
Correspondence
Membership
Series III. Treasurer
Series IV. Business Office
Series V. Committees
Series VI. Branches and Divisions
Series VII. Meetings
Executive Council
Annual Meeting
Decennial Review Conference
Miscellaneous Conferences
Series VIII. Publications
Bibliography and Index
Miscellaneous Publications
In Vitro
Series IX. W. Alton Jones Cell Science Center (WAJCSC) [Unprocessed.]
No restrictions.
Finding aid available.
SARCV 1990-01, SARCV 1990-02, SARCV 1991-01, SARCV 1992-02, SARCV 1992-03, SARCV 1998-06, SARCV 2000-09, SARCV 2000-12, SARCV 2004-05, SARCV 2008-04, SARCV 2009-05, SARCV 2010-003, SARCV 2010-005, SARCV 2011-06, SARCV 2012-01; The Tissue Culture Association Archives was donated in multiple accessions and sent from the TCA offices in Columbia, Maryland by William Momberger, the then Executive Director. The first accession arrived in August 1990 and contained 39 boxes. In December 1990 a second accession was received containing audiotapes of TCA meetings for the years 1975–1984. Additionally, in October 1991, 19 boxes of records and several microfilms were sent. A later accession of TCA materials arrived in January 1992 and contained a run of the Index of Tissue Culture from 1966–1979. Ten further accessions arrived between 1998 and 2012.
Society for In Vitro Biology; Tissue Culture Association Archives; Tissue culture Societies, etc.; Society for In Vitro Biology Archives; In Vitro
Center for Biological Sciences Archives. Accessed November 18, 2015.
Society for In Vitro Biology (formerly the Tissue Culture Association) Homepage. Accessed November 18, 2015.
- Series I. President, 1940-1985; bulk 1960-1984; 8960 items (13.5 linear feet)
  Series I contains correspondence, constitutions and bylaws, reports and miscellaneous administrative material arranged into two sub-series: Correspondence and Administrative Files.
  - Subseries I.A. Correspondence, 1940-1984; 7,600 items (11.25 linear feet)
    Correspondence files are arranged in date order by President, beginning with general correspondence, followed by subject files in alphabetical order.
    - Porter: General: 1940, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Porter: Tissue Culture Commission 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Porter: Tissue Culture Commission 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Porter: Tissue Culture Commission 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Porter: TCC Apparatus and Glassware 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Porter: TCC Conference 1946/11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Porter: TCC Testing Laboratory 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Porter: TCC Constitution 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Porter: TCC Testing Laboratory 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harris: General 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Harris: TCA Reorganization 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Harris: TCA Reorganization (Founding of ASCB) 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Weymouth: General 1960/5-1961/6 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Morgan: General 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Morgan: General 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Morgan: General 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Morgan: General 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Morgan: General 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Morgan: General 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Morgan: Ad Hoc Committees (Chang Report) 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Morgan: Chemically Defined Media 1963/1-3 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Morgan: Constitution Revision 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Morgan: Incorporation 1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Morgan: Local Committees 1962/11-1963/1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Morgan: Meeting (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Morgan: Pomerant Obituaries 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Morgan: Rutter 1963/1-3 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Morgan: Sidman 1963/2-4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Morgan: Summer Course 1963/5-10 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Morgan: Symposium (Boston) 1963/2-5 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Merchant: General 1950-1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Merchant: Archives Committee 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Merchant: Bibliography 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Merchant: California Branch 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Merchant: Cesvet (Bibliography) 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Merchant: Committee on Standards 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Merchant: Decennial Review Conference 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Merchant: Executive Council 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Merchant: Film Library 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Merchant: Financial 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Merchant: Grants 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Merchant: Haematopoietic Symposium 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Merchant: Hetherington 1966/4-1967/5 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Merchant: Kruse 1966/6-1968/7 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Merchant: Meeting 1969 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Merchant: Meeting 1970 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Merchant: Membership Committee 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Merchant: Morgan 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Merchant: Murray 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Merchant: National Medal of Science 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Merchant: Nomenclature Committee 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Merchant: Nomenclature Committee 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Merchant: Nominating Committee 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Merchant: Osgood 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Merchant: Parker 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Merchant: Program Committee 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Merchant: Publications 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Merchant: Publications Committee 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Merchant: Publicity 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Merchant: Sections Organization 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Merchant: Sidman 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Merchant: Training Committee 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Merchant: Trustees 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Federoff: Personal Index File Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Federoff: General 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Federoff: General 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Federoff: General 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Federoff: American Type Culture Collection 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Federoff: Annual Meetings 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Federoff Annual Meeting 1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Federoff: Annual Meeting 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Federoff: Annual Meeting 1973 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Federoff: Annual Meeting 1974 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Federoff: Annual Meeting 1975 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Federoff: Annual Meeting Feedback 1969 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Federoff: Bibliography Background 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Federoff: Bibliography Subcommittee 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Federoff: Board of Governors 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Federoff: Board of Governors 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Federoff: Branches 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Federoff: Branches/California 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Federoff: Branches/Central States 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Federoff: Cesvet 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Federoff: Claude, Albert (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Federoff: Committees/Archives 1964-1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Federoff: Committees/Chemically Defined Media 1969-1971/7 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Federoff: Committees/Chemically Defined Media 1971/8-1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Federoff: Committees/Contaminations in Cells and Tissue Culture 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Federoff: Committees/General 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Federoff: Committees/Materials and Supplies 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Federoff: Committees/Membership 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Federoff: Committees/Nominating 1964-1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Federoff: Committees/Program 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Federoff: Committees/Program 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Federoff: Committees/Program 1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Federoff: Committees/Program 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Federoff: Committees/Publicity & Endowment, Cell Science Center 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Federoff: Committees/Serum 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Federoff: Committees/Serum 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Federoff: Committees/Standards 1968 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Federoff: Council 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Federoff: Earle Award 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Federoff: Editorial Board 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Federoff: Executive Council (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Federoff: Fell Eulogy (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Federoff: Film Library 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Federoff: Financial (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Federoff: Invertebrate Tissue Culture 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Federoff: Legal 1971 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Federoff: Membership Inquiries/Problems 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Federoff: Media Development 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Federoff: Michigan Branch (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Federoff: Nerve Tissue Culture 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Federoff: Newsletter 1971 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Federoff: Pathology (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Federoff: Placement Service (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Federoff: Plant Tissue Division (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Federoff: Publication Board 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Federoff: Publication Board 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Federoff: Publications/In Vitro (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Federoff: Reorganization (TC) 1969 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Federoff: Research 1971 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Federoff: Reticuloendothelial Society 1969 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Federoff: Secretary 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Federoff: Selection of Director 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Federoff: Staff 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Federoff: Staff/Resumes (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Federoff: Sustaining Members 1969/7-11 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Federoff: Treasurer 1967-1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Federoff: Trustees/Corinell 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Federoff: WAJC Science Center 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Federoff: WAJC Science Center (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Federoff: WAJC Science Center/Dedication 1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Federoff: WAJC Science Center/Executive Board 1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Federoff: WAJC Science Center/Executive Board 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Federoff: WAJC Science Center/Executive Board 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Federoff: WAJC Science Center/Executive Board 1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Evans: General 1972-1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Evans: American Type Culture Collection 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Evans: Annual Report 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Evans: Bibliography 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Evans: Biological Stain Commission 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Evans: Biological Stain Commission 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Evans: California Branch 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Evans: Chemically Defined Media 1969-1974 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Evans: Decennial Review 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Evans: Dougall 1972 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Evans: Earle Award 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Evans: Editorial Board 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Evans: Education Committee 1970-1972/6 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Evans: Education Committee 1972/7-1974 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Evans: Election of Officers 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Evans: Endowment Committee 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Evans: Executive Board 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Evans: Exhibits 1972 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Evans: Federations of American Societies for Experimental Biology 1969 (Box 4, Folder 32)